<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dada Structures and Algorithms - exploration</title><link href="https://oskipa.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://oskipa.github.io/feeds/exploration.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://oskipa.github.io/</id><updated>2026-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Tries, Explorations, and Rehersals</title><link href="https://oskipa.github.io/tries-explorations-and-rehersals.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2026-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2026-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Hugo Estrada</name></author><id>tag:oskipa.github.io,2026-02-23:/tries-explorations-and-rehersals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My explorations are essays that attempt to capture the meaning of the word "essay" as a try, a test, a probe, a rehearsal. The goal is to explore a topic; to learn as I put together my thoughts on the subject. To admit ignorance; to imagine possible causes; to stare …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My explorations are essays that attempt to capture the meaning of the word "essay" as a try, a test, a probe, a rehearsal. The goal is to explore a topic; to learn as I put together my thoughts on the subject. To admit ignorance; to imagine possible causes; to stare in wonder at the mysteries of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If college essays can be thought as intellectual boxing, then my explorations should we thought as walking in a garden of ideas. We walk until we stop to admire a flower. We rest next to the fountain and stare at the blue patterns of its tiles. Following a secret path, we discover a lovely sculpture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of creating artificial certainty, I want us to boldly hold onto the fog of ignorance. This will keep us honest, but, more importantly, acknowledge the reality of the limits of our knowledge. What we often pass as wisdom and insights are often wild guesses. Our strong convictions hide teenage fears of inadecuacies and social humilliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We lose false certainty, but we regain our sense of wonder. Admiting that we don't understand the world transforms that world into the magical place it was when we were young children. Admitting ignorance kindles our imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My explorations are mostly inspired by the many Latin American essays I read over the years, especially those written by Octavio Paz. There is some influence from French essayists, indirectly, since French literature has been a massive influence to Spanish literature for two hundred years. Of the French essayist I have read, I especially like Camus, whose essays the Rebel and The Myth of Sisyphus made a huge impact in my late adolescence. If at any point you read some exploration, and it reads like a clumsy imitation of Paz or Camus, you are right; but keep in mind it was done unconsciously, out of admiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I must name De Montaigne, the inventor of the genre, whose essays do feel like attempts to put into words what he thought about different subjects. His essays are probably the strongest influence for my desire to write these explorations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="exploration"></category><category term="essays"></category></entry></feed>