<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dada Structures and Algorithms - try</title><link href="https://oskipa.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://oskipa.github.io/feeds/try.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://oskipa.github.io/</id><updated>2026-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>On Writing Poorly</title><link href="https://oskipa.github.io/on-writing-poorly.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2026-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2026-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Hugo Estrada</name></author><id>tag:oskipa.github.io,2026-01-27:/on-writing-poorly.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have been in situations where I have taught how to write. I learned that the biggest problem teaching writing is not spelling or adopting the correct word usage, but the emotional stress that people experience when they write. This stress comes from how we teach: we …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have been in situations where I have taught how to write. I learned that the biggest problem teaching writing is not spelling or adopting the correct word usage, but the emotional stress that people experience when they write. This stress comes from how we teach: we judge people by their writing. We claim we only judge the text, but everyone knows that this isn't true. Our writing reflects the way we speak; how we think; who we are. Telling a student how we are trying to help them by fixing mistakes is telling them that there is something defective about them. I recall thinking how composition classes had to have some kind of therapy component so that we could move on to learning puntuation conventions and how to organize our arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a fear of writing, just like there is a fear or math. They both come from our use of writing and math to quickly evaluate the worth of someone in our hierarchical society. Responding with fear and evasion is natural, because who wants to be made feel lesser than others? Made to feel ignorant? Reminded of their lower social status?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have noticed that some people who went to parrochial school take deep pride on how they learned not to end a sentence in a preposition. Linguistically this is wrong; ending an English with a preposition is fine. Yet these parrochial school alumni will gleefully contort their sentences like a Cirque du Soleil performer to proudly show to which social class they belong to. They have been taught that they are better than others, as individuals, for avoding sentences that end in prepositions. Going to a private school is really an accomplishment of the parents, not of themselves. Yet we keep running into these people happily pointing out the "mistakes" that others make, misspellings, violations of the subjective and so on. Are they helping others to become better writers? No, the point is for the to feel better and to castigate others for not sharing in their learning upbriging, for not belonging to the same social class. As such, they don't deserve a voice, an opinion. Others should dismiss their thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this is what many of us end up doing. We don't share what we think. We don't participate. We doubt ourselves as writer. Every sentence becomes torture because we carry the anxiety that we are making some mistake that we are not aware about. If we write, our notebooks are shameful secrets. When we see someone leafing through them, we panic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So many of us stop writing at all, which is exactly what the point of all of that intellectual bullying is meant to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am inviting you to rebel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write poorly if that is what we can do. In reality, that is the best that most of us can. That is fine, because we don't need to publish what we write. We don't even have to share it if we don't want to. We gain a lot from writing, because writing is not about writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing is thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So participate in thinking by writing. Express who you are; who your family is; the history of your ancestors. You don't need permissions to think or write the same way I don't need it. If we can talk, we can think, and if we think we can write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing poorly is made up in any case. All of the greatest writers violate most of the modern writing style guides. Cervantes wrote long, complicated sentences with constant halting asides. Melville's Moby Dick changes the narrative style.  Shakespeare often ends sentences with prepositions. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="try"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="cognition"></category><category term="class"></category></entry></feed>